<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Spread Security</title>
    <description>ICT Security thoughts
</description>
    <link>http://spreadsecurity.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://spreadsecurity.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 23:37:00 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 23:37:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The title of this blog is pretty self-explanatory: “Spread Security”, in other words, share knowledge to increase awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why I started this project is because Information Security is a very interesting argument which is getting more and more 
critical as time goes by due to the growing presence of devices on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this scenario it is important to understand what type of attacks are in the wild and how to secure our devices, i.e. our data, from 
malicious users trying to steal personal informations such as credentials and documents.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://192.168.1.200:4000/images/cybersecurity.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 800px; &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theory is fundamental in every discipline, but I think that to understand deeply some concepts it is a must to consider also practice.
This is why the idea is to show theory of attacks followed by “hands-on” demonstrations performed on a virtual laboratory environment.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Following a portion of the steps presented in the Penetration Testing Execution Standards (PTES), which represents a technical
guideline for performing a penetration test, i.e. a simulation of a real attack against a certain target, we will focus on the theory and
practice behind the following main phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information gathering or reconnaissance;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vulnerability analysis;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploitation;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post-exploitation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will see the huge amount of informations we can acquire about a certain target by simply crawling the Internet using proper searches
and tools; understanding how it is important to limit the visibility of our personal informations to public access is a first important
step in the road to security.
&lt;br /&gt;
Many times users are the same ones giving the attackers a huge help by simply leaving personal data publicly
available on the net.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We will go from Web Application testing (for example SQL Injection, Cross-Site Scripting, Local/Remote File Inclusion) to Client-side
exploitation taking advantage of vulnerabilities in the software installed on victim machines.
&lt;br /&gt;
Since today Social Engineering techniques represent one of the most effective way to gather informations as they are based on the weak link
of the chain, i.e. users, we will show how attackers use this “art” to trick victims to obtain remote access to their machines and 
how it can be combined with Man In The Middle attacks to steal confidential data.
&lt;br /&gt;
We will see how it is important to choose complex passwords for our accounts since the increasing power of processors makes dictionary 
and brute force attacks more and more effective. This type of attacks can be performed also in the case of Wi-Fi networks where we will
see some techniques to check if an access point is set up in a secure way. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Of course this is just a brief overview of the arguments treated in this blog, but I think it will give you an idea of what you can look
for here.
&lt;br /&gt;
I hope you will find this blog useful. Enjoy the reading and see you in the next post.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
References: http://www.pentest-standard.org&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 23:23:44 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://spreadsecurity.github.io/2016/07/05/introduction.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://spreadsecurity.github.io/2016/07/05/introduction.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

